Thirdly, if you are a working professional and
you have a corporate health insurance
plan, then
why should you have your own health insurance plan in addition to it
?  And fourth,
what are the things you should keep
in mind while buying health insurance.  Let's get started.  First of all,
what is the best time to buy health insurance?  What is the best age
?  The definition of insurance is that if something happens it
gives me financial protection.
For health insurance, that becomes X.
If hospitalization happens then give me
financial protection.  Now hospitalization
is never planned.  And there
are so many examples, friends, where the
entire savings and investments of families have been wiped
out.  Because without any
warning, without any planning, some
hospitalization has occurred.  That is why
health insurance is important.  Now that you
are as young and healthy as you are, if
you take out your health insurance then that is the
right time for me to do that.  Why?
Three reasons.  Number one, your premiums will be the lowest.
Because you are young, because you are
healthy.  Your risk of hospitalization is
so low that the insurance company will
give you maximum cover at minimum premium.  Reason number two is because the
likelihood of your hospitalization is so low,
you can also get no claim bonus year after year.
No Claim Bonus No Claim Bonus.  No
claim bonus is if you do
not make any claim
for the insurance in that entire year.  You were not hospitalized
and did not make any claim from the insurance company.
So you
get a no claim bonus paid on renewal at the end of the year through
which you will get more cover for the same premium.
So over the years your cover keeps
increasing for the same premium which can only happen if the
chances of your claim are very less
which is the case when we are healthy as when we are
young.  And number
three lower rejection rates.  If you
take an insurance at a young and healthy age,
then even if God forbid you get hospitalized,
your rejection rate will be
very low because it is quite possible
that there was nothing to suggest that you may have
hidden something or not disclosed any pre-existing disease,
so on and so
forth.  Because of these three reasons, I
genuinely think that the best time to buy
insurance for yourself and your family should be as early as possible.
I remember
I took insurance for my family at the age of 25.
So the way that I
organized myself is first it was me, my
parents and my sister.  So there was
an insurance plan for all four of us.  And then when I got married I
immediately took another
insurance plan for my wife and I.   I did
not link it with my parents' insurance.  And I will tell you why very soon.
And then when we had children,
we kept adding them gradually.  Keep increasing your premium
so that our cover also keeps increasing.
And now I have two insurances.  The forest that is
for my parents.  And I pay for
it.  But that is only for my parents.  It
charges a very high premium.
But that's just for those two people.
And that is great.  And then there is one insurance
that I have for myself which I started
at the age of 24.  Today I am 40, so in those 16
years my no claim bonus bonus bonus bonus bonus has
increased a lot.
I have worked with the same insurance company till date.  So it
worked out really, really well for me.  Now
I stressed a lot in the last video.  I am
repeating it again in this video.
Your parents' health
insurance plan should not be linked to your family's
health insurance plan.
Separate
insurance plan for parents.  How and why and
what are the things that should be kept in mind.
Please watch the previous video and
a dedicated plan for your family
which we are talking about today.  Now
comes the corporate health plan.
Many working professionals now
also get a corporate health insurance plan as part of a corporate benefit.
And a lot of people think that if
this is a corporate plan then it is great.
What is the need to get your own plan?
Because in that you yourself, your partner, your
children, your parents and in some cases
even your in-laws are covered.  So it
seams like the best plan ever.  You do
n't have to pay any expense for this.  The company is
bearing your expenses.  So it feels even
better.  But there are some limitations in this
which you need to know.  That is what I am
going to share right now.  Number one, this
health insurance plan will terminate as soon as you
leave the company.  So that means
if you are not ready to work in a company for your entire life then
please be sensible and buy a health
insurance plan for yourself.
It is important to recognize that
two health insurance plans can also be used in India.  There can be
only one plan for cashless at a time.
But
after that cashless payment, the additional amount that you have to pay
may not be completely covered by your cashless amount.
You
can also cover with another plan.  For
example, your hospital bill came to ₹4
lakh.  Your limit in your corporate insurance
is ₹2 lakh.  But you
also have your own ₹3 lakh plan.  So how can you do this
?  Your bill of ₹4 lakhs, you
can make ₹1 lakh cashless through your own plan.
And then you will pay the remaining ₹1 lakh
from your pocket.  And then using the ₹2
lakh corporate plan you will
file for its reimbursement.  For that you will
need original receipts.  You will
need all the original bills from the hospital which
you already get
on discharge.  You will submit that and then
you will get ₹1 lakh from your cover of ₹1 lakh.
So your ₹4 lakh will also be covered.  A
lot of people do not know that you can
also combine two insurances.  Which
is why please
keep your personal plan along with your corporate plan.  Number two.
Many companies have a concept of copay.  The
concept of copay is basically given so
that people do not misuse this corporate insurance.
This means
that whatever your bill comes, a certain
percentage of it will be covered by the company's insurance.
But you will have to pay a certain percentage from your pocket.
Usually companies pay 10 to 20%.
This means that if
your bill comes for ₹4 lakh and you have a corporate cover of ₹4 lakh,
then it will not happen that the
entire ₹4 lakh will be deducted from the corporate cover.  If
your copay is 10% then only ₹60000 will be spent
from this corporate plan and you will have to pay ₹400
from your pocket to make up for
this 4 lakh bill.  So please check whether there is any
copay clause in your corporate health insurance plan or not.  If yes, then that
again is a limitation which you should not have ideally
in a health insurance
plan.  And thirdly by design because this
company is bearing the cost.  Their coverage is
limited.  Usefully I have seen that
on Life they offer plans ranging from ₹1 to ₹1 lakh.
So, if you and your partner have
two children, then you will probably
get a plan of three to four or maximum ₹6 to ₹8 lakh.
But if you buy it yourself, you can
decide on the coverage you want.  You can avail coverage of ₹1 lakh
for a family of two
adults and two kids.  Or if you are just two
adults, you can take a plan of ₹5 lakh.
It basically becomes your choice and there is
continuity in it because you will never
leave yourself, even if you leave this job,
you will continue renewing this
policy which is why again as I
repeat please keep your health insurance plan with corporate health insurance plan.
And then finally, when you are
looking for a health insurance plan for yourself,
what are the five things that you should keep in mind
so that you can choose the right health insurance
plan.  Number one, the right amount.
According to me, ₹2 to ₹5 lakh for adult and ₹1 lakh for
child should be the ideal cover amount.
Which means if you are two people then around Rs 5
lakh.  If you are two people and have one child then
5 lakh plus 1 lakh 6 lakh.  If you are two people
and have two children then Rs 7 lakh.  That should be roughly how
you determine how much amount
is necessary for you.  Of course it is finally
your decision.  But this is a nice
happy guiding metric according to me.  Second network
hospitals.  Whatever insurance you are taking,
how much network of cashless hospitals is there in it.  Whether there is a
cashless network where you are
or not.  Because it can be far away
but there are so many hospitals in the same vicinity where you are
which provide you cashless service
from the insurance company that you have bought it from.
Third is there is a facility for
lifetime renewal.  Like lifetime renewal
is very important because as you grow older
you may want to increase your cover
or you can renew it continuously
forever and ever, so this should be
an option because some
insurance policies have a cap that
you can renew only for so many years, you
cannot renew it for lifetime.  Fourth,
are medical checkups part of the plan or
not?  If you are young then
we easily ignore the question that why do we need to get a medical
checkup done?  He is still young.  Right now
everything is going well.  But that is if
your insurance provides you free
medical checkups per year.  So there is an incentive to
not waste it and use it.
So please go with plans that
provide you with a medical checkup.  And
fifth maternity benefits.  Maternity
benefits are very diverse as many
insurance plans offer very restricted
maternity benefits.  Even though
the amount is very small, some have
very long waiting periods.  So, if you are
planning your family, it is important that
you take the maximum amount for the
maternity benefit.